[
   {
     "question":"Which among the following about the river Ravi are correct?\n1. The length of the river is about 720 kilometers\n2. It is a trans-boundary river of India and Pakistan\n3. It originates near Rothang Pass in Kullu\nChoose the correct option from the codes given below :",
     "optionA":"1 & 2",
     "optionB":"1 & 3",
     "optionC":"2 & 3",
     "optionD":"1, 2 & 3",
     "correctAns":"1, 2 & 3"
   },
   {
     "question":"Kullu valley is formed by which of the following river?",
     "optionA":"Shyok",
     "optionB":"Gilgit",
     "optionC":"Beas",
     "optionD":"Ravi",
     "correctAns":"Beas"
   },
   {
     "question":"Which of the following rivers is the longest of the five rivers that flow through the Punjab region?",
     "optionA":"Jhelum",
     "optionB":"Chenab",
     "optionC":"Sutlej",
     "optionD":"Beas",
     "correctAns":"Sutlej"
   },
   {
     "question":"Which among the following about the Ghaggar river are correct?\n1. It is also known as Saraswati river\n2. It is an inland drainage\n3. It flows only during the monsoon season\n4. Kaushalya and Markanda are the tributaries of the river\nChoose the correct option from the codes given below :",
     "optionA":"1 & 2",
     "optionB":"1, 2 & 3",
     "optionC":"2, 3 & 4",
     "optionD":"1, 2, 3 & 4",
     "correctAns":"1, 2, 3 & 4"
   },
   {
     "question":"Arrange the following tributaries of the Indus river as per the descending order of their length\n1. Satluj\n2. Chenab3. Jhelum\n4. Beas\nChoose the correct option from the codes given below :",
     "optionA":"1, 2, 3, 4",
     "optionB":"2, 1, 3, 4",
     "optionC":"1, 3, 2, 4",
     "optionD":"4, 3, 1, 2",
     "correctAns":"1, 2, 3, 4"
   },
   {
     "question":"What percent of the total area of India is occupied by the river Ganga?",
     "optionA":"5.87%",
     "optionB":"10.62%",
     "optionC":"21.3%",
     "optionD":"26.3%",
     "correctAns":"26.3%"
   },
   {
     "question":"The Sundarbans delta is formed by the depositional action of which among the following rivers?\n1. Ganga\n2. Brahmaputra\n3. Meghna\n4. Yamuna\nChoose the correct option from the codes given below :",
     "optionA":"1 & 2",
     "optionB":"1, 2 & 3",
     "optionC":"1, 3 & 4",
     "optionD":"1, 2, 3 & 4",
     "correctAns":"1, 2 & 3"
   },
   {
     "question":"Arrange the following tributaries of Ganga from east to west direction\n1. Kosi\n2. Yamuna\n3. Gomti\n4. Damodar\nChoose the correct option from the codes given below :",
     "optionA":"4, 2, 1, 3",
     "optionB":"4, 1, 3, 2",
     "optionC":"3, 4, 1, 2",
     "optionD":"3, 2, 1, 4",
     "correctAns":"4, 1, 3, 2"
   },
   {
     "question":"The Kota city is located beside which of the following rivers?",
     "optionA":"Betwa",
     "optionB":"Chambal",
     "optionC":"Ken",
     "optionD":"Son",
     "correctAns":"Chambal"
   },
   {
     "question":"Which among the following matches of types of forests and areas associated are correct?\n1. Tropical rainforests- Andaman and Nicobar islands\n2. Monsoon forests- Uttar Pradesh and Bihar\n3. Thorny bushes- Rajasthan and Gujarat\n4. Tidal forests- Sunderbans\nChoose the correct option from the codes given below :",
     "optionA":"1 & 2",
     "optionB":"1, 2 & 3",
     "optionC":"1, 3 & 4",
     "optionD":"1, 2, 3 & 4",
     "correctAns":"1, 2, 3 & 4"
   },
   {
     "question":"Which of the following types of forest occupies the largest area?",
     "optionA":"Montane wet temperate forest",
     "optionB":"Sub-tropical dry evergreen forest",
     "optionC":"Tropical moist deciduous forest",
     "optionD":"Tropical wet evergreen forest",
     "correctAns":"Tropical moist deciduous forest"
   },
   {
     "question":"Ranganathittu Bird Sanctuary is situated in which of the following states of India?",
     "optionA":"Tamil Nadu",
     "optionB":"Andhra Pradesh",
     "optionC":"Kerala",
     "optionD":"Karnataka",
     "correctAns":"Karnataka"
   },
   {
     "question":"How many major bio-geographic regions are there in India?",
     "optionA":"9",
     "optionB":"10",
     "optionC":"11",
     "optionD":"12",
     "correctAns":"10"
   },
   {
     "question":"Which among the following matches of Forest institutes and their location are correct?\n1. The Temperate Forest Research Centre- Shimla\n2. The Institute of Forest Genetics and Tree Breeding- Coimbatore\n3. The Institute of Rain and Moist Deciduous Forest- Jorhat\n4. The Centre for Forest Productivity- Kolkata\nChoose the correct option from the codes given below :",
     "optionA":"1 & 2",
     "optionB":"2 & 4",
     "optionC":"1, 2 & 3",
     "optionD":"1, 2, 3 & 4",
     "correctAns":"1, 2 & 3"
   },
   {
     "question":"Which among the following matches of ore and their metals are correct?\n1. Limonite- Iron\n2. Chalcopyrite- Copper\n3. Bauxite- Aluminium\n4. Monazite- Thorium\nChoose the correct option from the codes given below :",
     "optionA":"1 & 2",
     "optionB":"1, 2 & 3",
     "optionC":"1, 3 & 4",
     "optionD":"1, 2, 3 & 4",
     "correctAns":"1, 2, 3 & 4"
   },
   {
     "question":"Turamdih of Jharkhand is famous for which of the following mineral deposit?",
     "optionA":"Diamond",
     "optionB":"Bauxite",
     "optionC":"Copper",
     "optionD":"Uranium",
     "correctAns":"Uranium"
   },
   {
     "question":"Which among the following states is the leading producer of Gypsum?",
     "optionA":"Odisha",
     "optionB":"Karnataka",
     "optionC":"Rajasthan",
     "optionD":"Madhya Pradesh",
     "correctAns":"Rajasthan"
   },
   {
     "question":"Kalakot tertiary coalfield is located in which of the following places of India?",
     "optionA":"Himalayan mountain region",
     "optionB":"Cardamom hills of Kerala",
     "optionC":"Damodar river basin of Jharkhand and West Bengal",
     "optionD":"Brahmaputra river basin Assam",
     "correctAns":"Himalayan mountain region"
   },
   {
     "question":"Which among the following states ranks first in the production of thermal power?",
     "optionA":"Andhra Pradesh",
     "optionB":"Gujarat",
     "optionC":"Maharashtra",
     "optionD":"Karnataka",
     "correctAns":"Maharashtra"
   },
   {
     "question":"Which among the following about the Forest Report is/ are correct?\n1. ISFR is published by Forest Survey of India (FSI) biennially\n2. ISFR 2019 is the 16th report in the pattern\n3. Apart from forest and tree survey it also measures carbon stock and forest fires related data\n4. ISFR 2019 has created the National forest inventory on produce from forests for the first time\nChoose the correct option from the codes given below :",
     "optionA":"1 & 2",
     "optionB":"1, 2 & 4",
     "optionC":"2, 3 & 4",
     "optionD":"1, 2, 3 & 4",
     "correctAns":"1, 2, 3 & 4"
   },
   {
     "question":"Which among the following pairs are correctly matched?\n1. Gold- Kolar\n2. Coal- Jharia\n3. Copper- Khetri\n4. Iron- Kudremukh\nChoose the correct option from the codes given below :",
     "optionA":"1 & 2",
     "optionB":"2 & 4",
     "optionC":"3 & 4",
     "optionD":"1, 2, 3 & 4",
     "correctAns":"1, 2, 3 & 4"
   }
]